<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="alice_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <chapter>
        <heading> Chapter II </heading>
        <p> They were indeed a curious looking party that assembled on the bank—the birds with draggled
            feathers, the animals with their fur clinging close to them—all dripping wet, cross, and
            uncomfortable. The first question of course was, how to get dry: they had a consultation about
            this, and <yap><char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> hardly felt at all surprised at finding herself talking familiarly with the
            birds, as if she had known them all her life. Indeed, she had quite a long argument with the
            <char>Lory</char>, who at last turned sulky, and would only say "I am older than you, and must know best,"
            and this <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> would not admit without knowing how old the <char>Lory</char> was, and as the <char>Lory</char>
            positively refused to tell its age, there was nothing more to be <xpres>said</xpres>.</yap>
        </p>
        <p> At last <char>the mouse</char>, who seemed to have some authority among them, <xpres>called</xpres> out "sit down, all
            of you, and attend to me! I'll soon make you dry enough!" They all sat down at once,
            shivering, in a large ring, <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> in the middle, with her eyes anxiously fixed on <char>the mouse</char>,
            for she felt sure she would catch a bad cold if she did not get dry very soon. </p>
        <p> "Ahem!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, with a self-important air, "are you all ready? This is the driest
            thing I know. Silence all round, if you please! </p>
        <p> "<char>William the Conqueror</char>, whose cause was favoured by the pope, was soon submitted to by the
            English, who wanted leaders, and had been of late much accustomed to usurpation and conquest.
            <char>Edwin and Morcar</char>, the earls of Mercia and Northumbria—" </p>
        <p> "Ugh!" <xpres>said</xpres> the <char>Lory</char> with a shiver. </p>
        <p> "I beg your pardon?" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, frowning, but very politely, "did you speak?" </p>
        <p> "Not I!" <xpres>said</xpres> the <char>Lory</char> hastily. </p>
        <p> "I thought you did," <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, "I proceed. <char>Edwin and Morcar</char>, the earls of Mercia and
            Northumbria, declared for him; and even <char>Stigand</char>, the patriotic archbishop of Canterbury, found it
            advisable to go with <char>Edgar Atheling</char> to meet <char>William</char> and offer him the crown. <char>William's</char> conduct
            was at first moderate—how are you getting on now, dear?" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, turning to <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> as
            it spoke. </p>
        <p> "As wet as ever," <xpres>said</xpres> poor <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "it doesn't seem to dry me at all." </p>
        <p> "In that case," <xpres>said</xpres> the <char>Dodo</char> solemnly, rising to his feet, "I move that the meeting
            adjourn, for the immediate adoption of more energetic remedies—" </p>
        <p> "Speak English!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char species="nonhuman">the Duck</char>, "I don't know the meaning of half those long words, and
            what's more, I don't believe you do either!" And <char species="nonhuman">the Duck</char> quacked a comfortable laugh to
            itself. Some of the other birds tittered audibly. </p>
        <p> "I only meant to say," <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the dodo</char> in a rather offended tone, <plot>"that I know of a house near
            here, where we could get the young lady and the rest of the party dried, and then we could
            listen comfortably to the story which I think you were good enough to promise to tell us,"
            bowing gravely to <char>the mouse</char>.</plot>
        </p>
        <p> <char>the mouse</char> made no objection to this, and the whole party moved along the river bank, (for
            the pool had by this time began to flow out of the hall, and the edge of it was fringed with
            rushes and forget-me-nots,) in a slow procession, <char>the dodo</char> leading the way. After a time <char>the
                Dodo</char> became impatient, and, leaving <char species="nonhuman">the Duck</char> to bring up the rest of the party, moved on at a
            quicker pace with <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, the <char>Lory</char>, and the <char>Eaglet</char>, and soon brought them to a little cottage,
            and there they sat snugly by the fire, wrapped up in blankets, until the rest of the party had
            arrived, and they were all dry again. </p>
        <p> Then they all sat down again in a large ring on the bank, and begged <char>the mouse</char> to begin his
            story. </p>
        <p> "Mine is a long and a sad tale!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, turning to <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, and sighing. </p>
        <p> "It <uline>is</uline> a long tail, certainly," <xpres>said</xpres> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, looking down with wonder
            at <char>the mouse</char>'s tail, which was coiled nearly all round the party, "but why do you call it
            sad?" and she went on puzzling about this as <char>the mouse</char> went on speaking, so that her idea of
            the tale was something like this:
        </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_028.jpg"/>
        <yap><div class="poem">
            <l indent="">We lived beneath the mat </l>
            <l indent="3.5em">Warm and snug and fat</l>
            <l indent="7em">But one woe, &amp; that</l>
            <l indent="11.5em">Was the <uline>cat</uline>!</l>
            <l indent="13.5em">To our joys</l>
            <l indent="14em">a clog, In</l>
            <l indent="13.5em">our eyes a</l> 
            <l indent="11.5em">fog, On our</l>
            <l indent="9em">hearts a log</l>
            <l indent="7em"><uline>Was</uline> the dog!</l>
            <l indent="7em">When the</l>
            <l indent="3.5em">cat's away,</l>
            <l indent="2.5em">Then</l>
            <l indent="1.5em">the mice</l>
            <l indent="1.5em">will</l>
            <l indent="2.5em">play,</l>
            <l indent="3.5em">But, alas!</l>
            <l indent="4.5em">one day, (<uline>So</uline> they say)</l>
            <l indent="7em">Came the dog and</l>
            <l indent="12em">cat, Hunting</l>
            <l indent="16em">for a</l>
            <l indent="17em">rat,</l>
            <l indent="14.5em">Crushed</l>
            <l indent="13em">the mice</l>
            <l indent="11em">all flat;</l>
            <l indent="11em">Each</l>
            <l indent="10.5em">one</l>
            <l indent="10.5em">as</l>
            <l indent="10.5em">he</l>
            <l indent="10.5em">sat.</l>
            <l indent="11.5em">U</l>
            <l indent="12em">n</l>
            <l indent="12.5em">d</l>
            <l indent="13em">e</l>
            <l indent="13.5em">r</l>
            <l indent="14em">n</l>
            <l indent="14.5em">e</l>
            <l indent="15em">a</l>
            <l indent="15.5em">t</l>
            <l indent="16em">h</l>
            <l indent="16em">t</l>
            <l indent="16em">h</l>
            <l indent="16em">e</l>
            <l indent="15em">m</l>
            <l indent="14.5em">a</l>
            <l indent="14em">t</l>
            <l indent="13.5em">,</l>
            <l indent="8.5em">m r a W</l>
            <l indent="5.5em">g u n s &amp;</l>
            <l indent="3.5em">t a f &amp;</l>
            <l indent="1.5em">Think? </l> 
            <l indent="">of that!</l> 
        </div></yap>
        <!--we are NOT trying to do this better. leave as is or just replace with a high quality image-cv-->
        <p> "You are not attending!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char> to <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> severely, "what are you thinking of?" </p>
        <p> "I beg your pardon," <xpres>said</xpres> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> very humbly, "you had got to the fifth bend, I think?" </p>
        <p> "I had not!" <xpres>cried</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, sharply and very angrily. </p>
        <p> "A knot!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, always ready to make herself useful, and looking anxiously about her,
            "oh, do let me help to undo it!" </p>
        <p> "I shall do nothing of the sort!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the mouse</char>, getting up and walking away from the
            party, "you insult me by talking such nonsense!" </p>
        <p> "I didn't mean it!" pleaded poor <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "but you're so easily offended, you know." </p>
        <p> <char>the mouse</char> only growled in reply. </p>
        <p> "Please come back and finish your story!" <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> <xpres>called</xpres> after it, and the others all joined
            in chorus "yes, please do!" but <char>the mouse</char> only shook its ears, and walked quickly away, and
            was soon out of sight. </p>
        <p> "What a pity it wouldn't stay!" sighed <char>the lory</char>, and an old Crab took the opportunity of
            saying to its daughter "Ah, my dear! let this be a lesson to you never to lose <uline>your</uline>
            temper!" "Hold your tongue, Ma!" <xpres>said</xpres> the young Crab, a little snappishly, "you're enough to
            try the patience of an oyster!" </p>
        <p> "I wish I had our <char>Dinah</char> here, I know I do!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> aloud, addressing no one in
            particular, "she'd soon fetch it back!" </p>
        <p> "And who is <char>Dinah</char>, if I might venture to ask the question?" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the lory</char>. </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_031.jpg"/>
        <p> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> <xpres>replied</xpres> eagerly, for she was always ready to talk about her pet, "<char>Dinah</char>'s our cat. And
            she's such a capital one for catching mice, you can't think! And oh! I wish you could see her
            after the birds! Why, she'll eat a little bird as soon as look at it!" </p>
        <p> This answer caused a remarkable sensation among the party: some of the birds hurried off at
            once; one old magpie began wrapping itself up very carefully, remarking "I really must be
            getting home: the night air does not suit my throat," and a canary <xpres>called</xpres> out in a trembling
            voice to its children "come away from her, my dears, she's no fit company for you!" On various
            pretexts, they all moved off, and <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> was soon left alone. </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_033.jpg"/>
        <p>
            
        </p>
        <p> <litdev type="allit">She sat for some while sorrowful and silent</litdev>, but she was not long before she recovered her
            spirits, and began talking to herself again as usual: "I do wish some of them had stayed a
            <litdev type="allit">little longer!</litdev> and I was getting to be such friends with them—really <char>the lory</char> and I were
            almost like sisters! and so was that dear little Eaglet! And then <char species="nonhuman">the Duck</char> and <char>the dodo</char>! How
            nicely <char species="nonhuman">the Duck</char> sang to us as we came along through the water: and if the Dodo hadn't known
            the way to that nice little cottage, I don't know when we should have got dry again—" and
            there is no knowing how long she might have prattled on in this way, if she had not suddenly
            caught the sound of pattering feet. </p>
        <p> It was the white rabbit, trotting slowly back again, and looking anxiously about it as it
            went, as if it had lost something, and she heard it muttering to itself "the Marchioness! the
            Marchioness! oh my dear paws! oh my fur and whiskers! She'll have me executed, as sure as
            ferrets are ferrets!
            Where <uline>can</uline> I have dropped them, I wonder?" <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> guessed in a moment
            that it was looking for the nosegay and the pair of white kid gloves, and she began hunting
            for them, but they were now nowhere to be seen—everything seemed to have changed since her
            swim in the pool, and her walk along the river-bank with its fringe of rushes and
            forget-me-nots, and the glass table and the little door had vanished. </p>
        <p> Soon <char>the rabbit</char> noticed <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, as she stood looking curiously about her, and at once <xpres>said</xpres> in
            a quick angry tone, "why, Mary Ann! what <uline>are</uline> you doing out here? Go
            home this moment, and look on my dressing-table for my gloves and nosegay, and fetch them
            here, as quick as you can run, do you hear?" and <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> was so much frightened that she ran off
            at once, without saying a
            word, in the direction which <char>the rabbit</char> had pointed out. </p>
        <p> She soon found herself in front of a neat little house, on the door of which was a bright
            brass plate with the name <b>W. RABBIT, ESQ.</b> She went in, and hurried upstairs, for fear
            she should meet the real Mary Ann and be turned out of the house before she had found the
            gloves: she knew that one pair had been lost in the hall, "but of course," thought <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "it
            has plenty more of them in its house. How queer it seems to be going messages for a rabbit! I
            suppose <char>Dinah</char>'ll be sending me messages next!" And she began fancying the sort of things that
            would happen: "Miss <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>! come here directly and get ready for your walk!" "Coming in a
            minute, nurse! but I've got to watch this mousehole till <char>Dinah</char> comes back, and see that the
            mouse doesn't get out—" "only I don't think," <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> went on, "that they'd let <char>Dinah</char> stop in
            the house, if it began ordering people about like that!"
        </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_035.jpg"/>
        <p> By this time she had found her way into a tidy little room, with a table in the window on
            which was a looking-glass and, (as <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> had hoped,) two or three pairs of tiny white, kid
            gloves: she took up a pair of gloves, and was just going to leave the room, when her eye fell
            upon a little bottle that stood near the looking-glass: there was no label on it this time
            with the words "drink me," but nonetheless she uncorked it and put it to her lips: "I know
            something interesting is sure to happen," she <xpres>said</xpres> to herself, "whenever I eat or drink
            anything, so I'll see what this bottle does. I do hope it'll make me grow larger, for I'm
            quite tired of being such a tiny little thing!" </p>
        <p> <transform><plot>It did so indeed, and much sooner than she expected: before she had drunk half the bottle, she found her
            head pressing against the ceiling</plot>, and she stooped to save her neck from being broken</transform>, and
            hastily put down the bottle, saying to herself "that's quite enough—I hope I sha'n't grow any
            more—I wish I hadn't drunk so much!" </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_036.jpg"/>
        <p> Alas! it was too late: she went on growing and growing, and very soon had to kneel down: in
            another minute there was not room even for this, and she tried the effect of lying down, with
            one elbow against the door, and the other arm curled round her head. Still she went on
            growing, and as a last resource she put one arm out of the window, and one foot up the
            chimney, and <xpres>said</xpres> to herself "now I can do no more—what <uline>will</uline> become of
            me?" </p>
        <p>
            
        </p>
        <p> Luckily for <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, the little magic bottle had now had its full effect, and she grew no
            larger; still it was very uncomfortable, and as there seemed to be no sort of chance of ever
            getting out of the room again, no wonder she felt unhappy. "It was much pleasanter at home,"
            thought poor <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "when one wasn't always growing larger and smaller, and being ordered
            about by mice and rabbits—I almost wish I hadn't gone down that rabbit-hole, and yet, and
            yet—it's rather curious, you know, this sort of life. I do wonder what <uline>can</uline> have happened to me! When I used to read fairy-tales, I fancied that sort of
            thing never happened, and now here I am in the middle of one! There out to be a book written
            about me, that there ought! and when I grow up I'll write one—but I'm grown up now" <xpres>said</xpres> she
            in a sorrowful tone, "at least there's no room to grow up any more <uline>here</uline>." </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_037.jpg"/>
        <p> "But then," thought <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "shall I <uline>never</uline> get any older than I am now? That'll be a
            comfort, one way—never to be an old woman—but then—always to have lessons to learn! Oh, I
            shouldn't like <uline>that</uline>!" </p>
        <p> "Oh, you foolish <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>!" she <xpres>said</xpres> again, "how can you learn lessons in here? Why, there's
            hardly room for you, and no room at all for any lesson-books!" </p>
        <p> And so she went on, taking first one side, and then the other, and making quite a
            conversation of it altogether, but after a few minutes she heard a voice outside, which made
            her stop to listen. </p>
        <p> "Mary Ann! Mary Ann!" <xpres>said</xpres> the voice, "fetch me my gloves this moment!" Then came a little
            pattering of feet on the stairs: <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> knew it was <char>the rabbit</char> coming to look for her, and she
            trembled till she shook the house, quite forgetting that she was now about a thousand times as
            large as <char>the rabbit</char>, and had no reason to be afraid of it. Presently <char>the rabbit</char> came to the
            door, and tried to open it, but as it opened inwards, and <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>'s elbow was against it, the
            attempt proved a failure. <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> heard it say to itself "then I'll go round and get in at the window." </p>
        <p> "<uline>That</uline> you wo'n't!" thought <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, and, after waiting till she fancied
            she heard <char>the rabbit</char>, just under the window, she suddenly spread out her hand, and made a
            snatch in the air. She did not get hold of anything, but she heard a little <litdev type="onomatopoeia">shriek</litdev> and a fall
            and a crash of breaking glass, from which she concluded that it was just possible it had
            fallen into a cucumber-frame, or something of the sort. </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_040.jpg"/>
        <p> Next came an angry voice—<char>the rabbit</char>'s—"Pat, Pat! where are you?" And then a voice she had
            never heard before, "shure then I'm here! digging for apples, anyway, yer honour!" </p>
        <p> "Digging for apples indeed!" <xpres>said</xpres> <char>the rabbit</char> angrily, "here, come and help me out of <uline>this</uline>!"—Sound of more breaking glass. </p>
        <p> "Now, tell me, Pat, what is that coming out of the window?" </p>
        <p> "Shure it's an arm, yer honour!" (He pronounced it "arrum".) </p>
        <p> "An arm, you goose! Who ever saw an arm that size? Why, it fills the whole window, don't you
            see?" </p>
        <p> "Shure, it does, yer honour, but it's an arm for all that." </p>
        <p> "Well, it's no business there: go and take it away!" </p>
        <p> There was a long silence after this, and <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> could only hear whispers now and then, such
            as "shure I don't like it, yer honour, at all at all!" "do as I tell you, you coward!" and at
            last she spread out her hand again and made another snatch in the air. This time there were
            <uline>two</uline> little shrieks, and more breaking glass—"what a number of
            cucumber-frames there must be!" thought <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>, "I wonder what they'll do next! As for pulling
            me out of the window, I only wish they <uline>could</uline>! I'm sure <uline>I</uline> don't want to stop in here any longer!" </p>
        <p> She waited for some time without hearing anything more: at last came a rumbling of little cart-wheels, and
            the sound of a good many voices all talking together: she made out the words "where's the
            other ladder?—why, I hadn't to bring but one, <char>Bill</char>'s got the other—here, put 'em up at this
            corner—no, tie 'em together first—they don't reach high enough yet—oh, they'll do well enough,
            don't be particular—here, <char>Bill</char>! catch hold of this rope—will the roof bear?—mind that loose
            slate—oh, it's coming down! heads below!—" (a loud crash) "now, who did that?—it was <char>Bill</char>, I
            fancy—who's to go down the chimney?—nay, <uline>I</uline> sha'n't! <uline>you</uline> do it!—<uline>that</uline> I won't then—<char>Bill</char>'s got to go down—here,
            <char>Bill</char>! the master says you've to go down the chimney!" </p>
        <p> "Oh, so <char>Bill</char>'s got to come down the chimney, has he?" <xpres>said</xpres> <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> to herself, "why, they seem
            to put everything upon <char>Bill</char>! I wouldn't be in <char>Bill</char>'s place for a good deal: the fireplace is a
            pretty tight one, but I <uline>think</uline> I can kick a little!" </p>
        <p> She drew her foot as far down the chimney as she could, and waited till she heard a little animal (she
            couldn't guess what sort it was) scratching and scrambling in the chimney close above her:
            then, saying to herself "this is <char>Bill</char>," she gave one sharp kick, and waited again to see what
            would happen next. </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_043.jpg"/>
        <p> The first thing was a general chorus of "there goes <char>Bill</char>!" then <char>the rabbit</char>'s voice alone
            "catch him, you by the hedge!" then silence, and then another confusion of voices, "how was
            it, old fellow? what happened to you? tell us all about it." </p>
        <p> Last came a little feeble squeaking voice, ("that's <char>Bill</char>" thought <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char>,) which <xpres>said</xpres> "well,
            I hardly know—I'm all of a fluster myself—something comes at me like a Jack-in-the-box, and
            the next minute up I goes like a rocket!" "And so you did, old fellow!" <xpres>said</xpres> the other
            voices.
        </p>
        <p> "We must burn the house down!" <xpres>said</xpres> the voice of <char>the rabbit</char>, and <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> <xpres>called</xpres> out as loud as
            she could "if you do, I'll set <char>Dinah</char> at you!" This caused silence again, and while <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> was
            thinking "but how can I get <char>Dinah</char> here?" she found to her great delight that she was getting
            smaller: very soon she was able to get up out of the uncomfortable position in which she had
            been lying, and in two or three minutes more she was once more three inches high. </p>
        <p> She ran out of the house as quick as she could, and found quite a crowd of little animals
            waiting outside—guinea-pigs, white mice, squirrels, and "<char>Bill</char>" a little green lizard, that was
            being supported in the arms of one of the guinea-pigs, while another was giving it something
            out of a bottle. They all made a rush at her the moment she appeared, but <char type="main" species="human">Alice</char> ran her
            hardest, and soon found herself in a thick wood. </p>
        <image source="au-images/image_045.jpg"/>
        
        <image source="au-images/image_046.jpg"/>
        <p>
            
        </p>
    </chapter>
</root>
