<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="alice_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root><chapter>
    <heading> Chapter III </heading>
    <p> "The first thing I've got to do," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> to herself, as she wandered about in the wood,
        "is to grow to my right size, and the second thing is to find my way into that lovely garden.
        I think that will be the best plan." </p>
    <p> It sounded an excellent plan, no doubt, and very neatly and simply arranged: the only
        difficulty was, that she had not the smallest idea how to set about it, and while she was
        peering anxiously among the trees round her, a little sharp bark just over her head made her
        look up in a great hurry. </p>
    <p> An enormous <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy</char> was looking down at her with large round eyes, and feebly stretching out
        one paw, trying to reach her: "poor thing!" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> in a coaxing tone, and she tried hard to whistle to it, but
        she was terribly alarmed all the while at the thought that it might be hungry, in which case
        it would probably devour her in spite of all her coaxing. Hardly knowing what she did, she
        picked up a little bit of stick, and held it out to the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy:</char> whereupon the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy</char> jumped into
        the air off all its feet at once, and with a yelp of delight rushed at the stick, and made
        believe to worry it then <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> dodged behind a great thistle to keep herself from being run
        over, and, the moment she appeared at the other side, the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy</char> made another dart at the
        stick, and tumbled head over heels in its hurry to get hold: then <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, thinking it was very
        like having a game of play with a cart-horse, and expecting every moment to be trampled under
        its feet, ran round the thistle again: then the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy</char> begin a series of short charges at the
        stick, running a very little way forwards each time and a long way back, and barking hoarsely
        all the while, till at last it sat down a good way off, panting, with its tongue hanging out
        of its mouth, and its great eyes half shut.
    </p>
    <p> This seemed to <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> a good opportunity for making her escape. She set off at once, and ran
        till the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy's</char> bark sounded quite faint in the distance, and till she was quite tired and
        out of breath. </p>
    <p> "And yet what a dear little <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">puppy</char> it was!" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, as she leant against a buttercup to
        rest herself, and fanned herself with her hat. "I should have liked teaching it tricks, if—if
        I'd only been the right size to do it! Oh! I'd nearly forgotten that I've got to grow up
        again! Let me see; how <i>is</i> it to be managed? I suppose I ought to eat or drink something
        or other, but the great question is what?" </p> 
    <p> The great question certainly was, what? <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> looked all round her at the flowers and the
        blades of grass but could not see anything that looked like the right thing to eat under the
        circumstances. There was a large mushroom near her, about the same height as herself, and when
        she had looked under it, and on both sides of it, and behind it, it occurred to her to look
        and see what was on the top of it. </p>
    <p> She stretched herself up on tiptoe, and peeped over the edge of the mushroom, and her eyes immediately met
        those of a large blue <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>, which was sitting with its arms folded, quietly smoking a
        long hookah, and taking not the least notice of her or of anything else. </p>
    <image source="au-images/image_049.jpg"/>
    <p> For some time they looked at each other in silence: at last the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> took the hookah
        out of its mouth, and languidly addressed her. </p>
    <p> "Who are you?" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> This was not an encouraging opening for a conversation: <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> replied rather shyly, "I—I
        hardly know, sir, just at present—at least I know who I was when I got up this morning, but I
        think I must have been changed several times since that." </p>
    <p> "What do you mean by that?" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>, "explain yourself!" </p>
    <p> "I ca'n't explain <uline>myself</uline>, I'm afraid, sir," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "because I'm not myself, you see." </p>
    <p> "I don't see," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "I'm afraid I can't put it more clearly," <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> replied very politely, "for I ca'n't
        understand it myself, and really to be so many different sizes in one day is very confusing." </p>
    <p> "It isn't," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "Well, perhaps you haven't found it so yet," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "but when you have to turn into a
        chrysalis, you know, and then after that into a butterfly, I should think it'll feel a little
        queer, don't you think so?" </p>
    <p> "Not a bit," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "All I know is," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "it would feel queer to <uline>me</uline>." </p>
    <p> "<uline>You</uline>!" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> contemptuously, "who are you?" </p>
    <p> Which brought them back again to the beginning of the conversation: <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> felt a little
        irritated at the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> making such very short remarks, and she drew herself up and said
        very gravely "I think you ought to tell me who <uline>you</uline> are, first." </p>
    <p> "Why?" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> Here was another puzzling question: and as <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> had no reason ready, and the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> seemed to be in a
        very bad temper, she turned round and walked away. </p>
    <p> "Come back!" the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> called after her, "I've something important to say!" </p>
    <p> This sounded promising: <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> turned and came back again. </p>
    <p> "Keep your temper," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "Is that all?" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, swallowing down her anger as well as she could. </p>
    <p> "No," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> thought she might as well wait, as she had nothing else to do, and perhaps after all
        the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> might tell her something worth hearing. For some minutes it puffed away at its
        hookah without speaking, but at last it unfolded its arms, took the hookah out of its mouth
        again, and said "so you think you're changed, do you?" </p>
    <p> "Yes, sir," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "I ca'n't remember the things I used to know—I've tried to say "How
        doth the little busy bee" and it came all different!" </p>
    <p> "Try and repeat "You are old, father William"," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> folded her hands, and began: </p>
    <image source="au-images/image_052.jpg"/>
    <p>
        
    </p>
    <p class="center"> 1. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"You are old, father William," the young man said,</l>
            <l indent="i2">"And your hair is exceedingly white:</l>
            <l indent="i0">And yet you incessantly stand on your head—</l>
            <l indent="i2">Do you think, at your age, it is right?"</l>
        </div>
    </div> 
    <p class="center"> 2. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"In my youth," father William replied to his son,</l>
            <l indent="i2">"I feared it <uline>might</uline> injure the brain</l>
            <l indent="i0">But now that I'm perfectly sure I have none,</l>
            <l indent="i2">Why, I do it again and again."</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <image source="au-images/image_054.jpg"/>
    <p>
        
    </p>
    <p class="center"> 3. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"You are old," said the youth, "as I mentioned before,</l>
            <l indent="i2">And have grown most uncommonly fat:</l>
            <l indent="i0">Yet you turned a back-somersault in at the door—</l>
            <l indent="i2">Pray what is the reason of that?"</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <p class="center"> 4. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"In my youth," said the sage, as he shook his gray locks,</l>
            <l indent="i2">"I kept all my limbs very supple,</l>
            <l indent="i0">By the use of this ointment, five shillings the box—</l>
            <l indent="i2">Allow me to sell you a couple."</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <image source="au-images/image_056.jpg"/>
    <p>
        
    </p>
    <p class="center"> 5. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"You are old," said the youth, "and your jaws are too weak</l>
            <l indent="i2">For anything tougher than suet:</l>
            <l indent="i0">Yet you eat all the goose, with the bones and the beak—</l>
            <l indent="i2">Pray, how did you manage to do it?"</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <p class="center"> 6. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"In my youth," said the old man, "I took to the law,</l>
            <l indent="i2">And argued each case with my wife,</l>
            <l indent="i0">And <uline>the muscular strength</uline>, <uline>which it
                gave to my jaw</uline>,</l>
            <l indent="i2">Has lasted the rest of my life."</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <image source="au-images/image_058.jpg"/>
    <p>
        
    </p>
    <p class="center"> 7. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"You are old," said the youth; "one would hardly suppose</l>
            <l indent="i2">That your eye was as steady as ever:</l>
            <l indent="i0">Yet you balanced an eel on the end of your nose—</l>
            <l indent="i2">What made you so <uline>awfully</uline> clever?"</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <p class="center"> 8. </p>
    <div class="poem">
        <div class="stanza">
            <l indent="i0">"I have answered three questions, and that is enough,"</l>
            <l indent="i2">Said his father, "don't give yourself airs!</l>
            <l indent="i0">Do you think I can listen all day to such stuff?</l>
            <l indent="i2">Be off, or I'll kick you down stairs!"</l>
        </div>
    </div>
    <p>
        
    </p>
    <p> "That is not said right," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "Not quite right, I'm afraid," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> timidly, "some of the words have got altered." </p>
    <p> "It is wrong from beginning to end," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> decidedly, and there was silence
        for some minutes: the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> was the first to speak. </p>
    <p> "What size do you want to be?" it asked. </p>
    <p> "Oh, I'm not particular as to size," <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> hastily replied, "only one doesn't like changing
        so often, you know." </p>
    <p> "Are you content now?" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>. </p>
    <p> "Well, I should like to be a <uline>little</uline> larger, sir, if you wouldn't
        mind," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "three inches is such a wretched height to be." </p>
    <p> "It is a very good height indeed!" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> loudly and angrily, rearing itself
        straight up as it spoke (it was exactly three inches high). </p>
    <p> "But I'm not used to it!" pleaded poor <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> in a piteous tone, and she thought to herself
        "I wish the creatures wouldn't be so easily offended!" </p>
    <p> "You'll get used to it in time," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>, and it put the hookah into its mouth,
        and began smoking again.
    </p> 
    <p> This time <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> waited quietly until it chose to speak again: in a few minutes the
        <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char> took the hookah out of its mouth, and got down off the mushroom, and crawled away
        into the grass, merely remarking as it went; "the top will make you grow taller, and the stalk
        will make you grow shorter." </p>
    <p> "The top of <uline>what</uline>? the stalk of <uline>what</uline>?" thought
        <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>. </p>
    <image source="au-images/image_061.jpg"/>
    <p> "Of the mushroom," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">caterpillar</char>, just as if she had asked it aloud, and in another
        moment was out of sight. </p>
    <p> <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> remained looking thoughtfully at the mushroom for a minute, and then picked it and
        carefully broke it in two, taking the stalk in one hand, and the top in the other. </p>
    <trans><p> "<uline>Which</uline> does the stalk do?" she said, and nibbled a little bit of it
        to try; the next moment she felt a violent blow on her chin: it had struck her foot!
    </p></trans>
    <p> She was a good deal frightened by this very sudden change, but as she did not shrink any
        further, and had not dropped the top of the mushroom, she did not give up hope yet. There was
        hardly room to open her mouth, with her chin pressing against her foot, but she did it at
        last, and managed to bite off a little bit of the top of the mushroom. </p>
    
    <trans><p> "Come! my head's free at last!" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> in a tone of delight, which changed into alarm in
        another moment, when she found that her shoulders were nowhere to be seen: she looked down
        upon an immense length of neck, which seemed to rise like a stalk out of a sea of green leaves
        that lay far below her. </p></trans>
    <image source="au-images/image_062.jpg"/>  
    <p> 
        
    </p>
    <p> "What <uline>can</uline> all that green stuff be?" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "and where <uline>have</uline> my shoulders got to? And oh! my poor hands! how is it I ca'n't see
        you?" She was moving them about as she spoke, but no result seemed to follow, except a little
        rustling among the leaves. Then she tried to bring her head down to her hands, and was
        delighted to find that her neck would bend about easily in every direction, like a serpent.
        She had just succeeded in bending it down in a beautiful zig-zag, and was going to dive in
        among the leaves, which she found to be the tops of the trees of the wood she had been
        wandering in, when a sharp hiss made her draw back: a large <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char> had flown into her face,
        and was violently beating her with its wings. </p>
    <image source="au-images/image_063.jpg"/>
    <p> "Serpent!" screamed the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>. </p>
    <p> "I'm <uline>not</uline> a serpent!" said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> indignantly, "let me alone!"
    </p>
    <p> "I've tried every way!" the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char> said desperately, with a kind of sob: "nothing seems to
        suit 'em!" </p>
    <p> "I haven't the least idea what you mean," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>. </p>
    <p> "I've tried the roots of trees, and I've tried banks, and I've tried hedges," the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>
        went on without attending to her, "but them serpents! There's no pleasing 'em!" </p>
    <p> <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> was more and more puzzled, but she thought there was no use in saying anything till
        the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char> had finished. </p>
    <p> "As if it wasn't trouble enough hatching the eggs!" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>, "without being on the
        look out for serpents, day and night! Why, I haven't had a wink of sleep these three weeks!" </p>
    <p> "I'm very sorry you've been annoyed," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, beginning to see its meaning. </p>
    <p> "And just as I'd taken the highest tree in the wood," said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char> raising its voice to a
        shriek, "and was just thinking I was free of 'em at last, they must needs come down from the
        sky! Ugh! Serpent!" </p>
    <p> "But I'm <uline>not</uline> a serpent," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, "I'm a—I'm a—" </p>
    <p> "Well! <uline>What</uline> are you?" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>, "I see you're trying to invent
        something."
    </p>
    <p> "I—I'm a little girl," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, rather doubtfully, as she remembered the number of
        changes she had gone through. </p>
    <p> "A likely story indeed!" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>, "I've seen a good many of them in my time, but
        never <uline>one</uline> with such a neck as yours! No, you're a serpent, I know <uline>that</uline> well enough! I suppose you'll tell me next that you never tasted an
        egg!" </p>
    <p> "I <uline>have</uline> tasted eggs, certainly," said <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char>, who was a very truthful
        child, "but indeed I do'n't want any of yours. I do'n't like them raw." </p>
    <p> "Well, be off, then!" said the <char type = "side" species = "nonhuman">pigeon</char>, and settled down into its nest again. <char type = "main" species = "human">Alice</char> crouched
        down among the trees, as well as she could, as her neck kept getting entangled among the
        branches, and several times she had to stop and untwist it. Soon she remembered the pieces of
        mushroom which she still held in her hands, and set to work very carefully, nibbling first at
        one and then at the other, and growing sometimes taller and sometimes shorter, until she had
        succeeded in bringing herself down to her usual size. </p>
    <p> It was so long since she had been of the right size that it felt quite strange at first, but she got quite
        used to it in a minute or two, and began talking to herself as usual: "well! there's half my
        plan done now! How puzzling all these changes are! I'm never sure what I'm going to be, from
        one minute to another! However, I've got to my right size again: the next thing is, to get
        into that beautiful garden—how <uline>is</uline> that to be done, I wonder?" </p>
    <p> Just as she said this, she noticed that one of the trees had a doorway leading right into
        it. "That's very curious!" she thought, "but everything's curious today: I may as well go in."
        And in she went. </p>
    <p> Once more she found herself in the long hall, and close to the little glass table: "now,
        I'll manage better this time" she said to herself, and began by taking the little golden key,
        and unlocking the door that led into the garden. Then she set to work eating the pieces of
        mushroom till she was about fifteen inches high: then she walked down the little passage: and
        <uline>then</uline>—she found herself at last in the beautiful garden, among the
        bright flowerbeds and the cool fountains. </p>
    <image source="au-images/image_067.jpg"/>
    
    <image source="au-images/image_068.jpg"/>
    <p>
        
    </p>
</chapter></root>